PENELOPE HOW

Data scientist, Ph.D.

Nuuk, Greenland

@ pho@geus.dk

% pennyhow.github.io

PennyHow

DrPennyHow



OVERVIEW

Data scientist based in Nuuk, Greenland with a strong background in cryospheric sciences. Extensive skills in programming, including the development of the pypromice Python package for operational data production from the PROMICE and GC-Net automated weather station network. Distributed two open-source photogrammetry software (Pointcatcher, PyTrx) for extracting physical measurements from optical imagery during M.Sc. and Ph.D. education. Accomplished glacier fieldworker in Greenland, Svalbard and Iceland. Experienced operating in diverse working environments, from teamwork in small groups to collaborations in international project consortiums.

EXPERIENCE

Data scientist

Geological Survey of Denmark and Greenland (GEUS), Greenland 2021-present

- Focused on data production from automated weather stations
- Responsible for operational processing from over 30 weather stations located on the Greenland Ice Sheet
- Production and maintenance of Python packages
- Documentation and dissemination of programming resources to researchers
- Coordination of department activities with Greenland research institutes and partners

Remote Sensing Specialist

Asiaq Greenland Survey, Greenland

2019-21

- Using remote sensing to monitor the landscape of Greenland, including ice sheet change, hydrology, and permafrost
- Responsible for the automisation and documentation of scientific pipelines, data visualisation, and statistical analysis
- Projects included the ESA Glaciers CCI ('An Inventory of Ice Marginal Lakes in Greenland'), and the ESA Greenland Ice Sheet CCI+ (responsible for data processing and analysis of supraglacial lake changes in Greenland)

Postdoctoral Research Associate

University of York, UK

2018-19

- Appointed to the project 'Archival Polar Photography Unearthing the Forgotten Record of Glacier Change'
- Implemented photogrammetry and computer vision techniques to extract measurements from archive imagery and examine glacier change in Greenland

SKILLS

Python
Bash
Javascript
Matlab
IDL
LaTeX

Linux Apple Windows



EDUCATION

Ph.D. Atmospheric and Environmental Sciences

University of Edinburgh, UK, 2014-18

Thesis title: Dynamical change at tidewater glaciers examined using time-lapse photogrammetry

External Ph.D. candidate

University Centre in Svalbard, Svalbard, 2014-18

Field demonstrator and lecturer for Glaciology (AG-325 and AG-347) and Remote Sensing of the Cryosphere (AGF-312) courses

M.Sc. (By Research) Environmental Science

Lancaster University, UK, 2012-13

Dissertation title: Measuring glacier movement and its influences using a new approach in terrestrial time-lapse techniques

B.Sc. (Hons) Physical Geography (4-year Australasia course)

Lancaster University, UK, 2008-12

First class degree. Dissertation title: Linking glacier hypsometry to meltwater isotopic composition

GRANTS/AWARDS

ESA Living Planet Fellowship (2021–24)

Examining Greenland's Ice Marginal Lakes Under a Changing Climate (GrIML)

UK-Greenland Arctic Research Bursaries Scheme (2023)

A flagship glacier-fjord monitoring programme in Nuup Kangerlua

University of Edinburgh Postdoctoral & Early Career Researcher Exchanges (2016)

Ph.D. placement at Norwegian Polar Institute, Tromsø

University of Edinburgh Meiklejohn Fund (2016)

Examining calving dynamics at a surge-type glacier in Svalbard using terrestrial time-lapse photogrammetry

University of Edinburgh Moray Endowment Fund (2015)

Monitoring glacier-volcano interactions at the Mýrdalsjökull ice cap, Iceland, using permanent terrestrial time-lapse platforms

SELECT PUBLICATIONS

- P How et al. (2023). pypromice: A Python package for processing automated weather station data. Journal of Open Source Software, 8(86), 5298, doi:10.21105/joss.05298
- P How et al. (2021) Greenland-wide inventory of ice marginal lakes using a multi-method approach. Scientific Reports 11, 4481. doi:10.1038/s41598-021-83509-1
- P How et al. (2020) PyTrx: A Python-Based Monoscopic Terrestrial Photogrammetry Toolset for Glaciology Frontiers in Earth Science 8, 21. doi:10.3389/feart.2020.00021
- P How et al. (2018) Calving controlled by melt-under-cutting: detailed calving styles revealed through time-lapse observations. Annals of Glaciology 60, 113-127. doi:10.1017/aog.2018.28

FURTHER EDUCATION

SAR and InSAR processing course (2019)

GAMMA Remote Sensing, Switzerland

Python object-oriented computing design (2015)

University of Edinburgh M.Sc. course, UK

Mini- and micro-uncrewed aerial vehicles (UAVs) for the Environmental Sciences (2014)

NERC Advanced Training course hosted by Scottish Association for Marine Science (SAMS), UK

MOST PROUD OF



pypromice conda distribution, 2023

After a lengthy review process, pypromice became my first Python package distributed through conda-forge

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Glacier dynamics

Time-lapse photogrammetry

Climate data analysis

Remote sensing

MEMBERSHIPS

- International Glaciological Society (IGS)
- European Geosciences Union (EGU)

LANGUAGES

English (mother tongue)

Danish (basic)

HOBBIES

Sailing

Hunting

Running

Squash

REFEREES

Signe Bech Andersen

Glaciology and Climate section leader Geological Survey of Denmark and Greenland (GEUS)

@ siba@geus.dk

Robert Fausto

PROMICE programme manager Geological Survey of Denmark and Greenland (GEUS)

@ rsf@geus.dk

Adrian Luckman

Professor of Glaciology Swansea University

@ a.luckman@swansea.ac.uk